ACTWU's Conventions Records 5619/028
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Conventions Records
1972-1987
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America
Textile Workers Union of America
5619/028
3.25 cubic feet
3.3 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of convention transcripts and other convention material from the 1972 Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America convention, the 1974 Textile Workers' Union of America convention, the 1976 Amalgamate Clothing and Textile Workers' Union merger convention, and the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union triennial conventions for 1978, 1981, 1984, and 1987.
6826503
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
May 21, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America And all other 5619 collections.
Textile industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing trade -- New York (State) -- New York; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE) --Archives; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
6826503
- Resolutions Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Material, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Statements on Staff, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Sergeants-At-Arms, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Tellers, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Committee Distributions Lists, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Committee Designations Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Committee Final Lists, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  See also Box 4 for more information on Committee Members
- Resolutions From Affiliates, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Resolutions. A: Amalgamated Insurance Program. Notes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Resolutions. A: Amalgamated Insurance Program., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Resolutions. A: Amalgamated Pension Program. Notes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Resolutions. A: Amalgamated Pension Program., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Resolutions. A: Industrial Matters, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Resolutions. A: Law and Constitution, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Resolutions. A1: Report to the GEB, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Resolutions. A2: Organization, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Resolutions. A3: Union Label, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Resolutions. A4: Amalgamated Medical Care, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Resolutions. A5: Amalgamated Day Care Centers, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Resolutions. A6: Amalgamated Education Program, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Resolutions. A8: Amalgamated Housing, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Resolutions. A9: Amalgamated Retiree Services, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Resolutions. B: Farm Workers, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Resolutions. B: Martin Luther King Legislation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Resolutions. B: Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Resolutions. B1: Statement on Education, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Includes Wage-Price Freeze
- Resolutions. B2: Fair Labor Standards Act, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Includes 4 day, 40 Hour Week
- Resolutions. B4: Social Security, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Resolutions. B5: Workmen's Compensation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Resolutions. B7: Political Education, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Resolutions. B8: Crisis of the Cities, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Resolutions. B9: Education, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Resolutions. B10: The Environment, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Resolutions. B11: NLRB and Taft-Hartley, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Resolutions. B12: Women Workers, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Resolutions. B13: Nation's Health, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Resolutions. B14: Consumer Protection, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Resolutions. B15: Civil Rights, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Resolutions. B18: Occupational Safety and Health, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Resolutions. B19: Unemployment Insurance, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Resolutions. C2: Imports, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Resolutions. C3: Foreign Policy, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Resolutions. C4: Boys and Girls Town of Italy, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Resolutions. C6: Italian-American Labor Council, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Resolutions. C9: Israel and Histadrut, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- TWUA Convention. Decorations, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- TWUA Convention. Entertainment, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- TWUA Convention. Agenda, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- TWUA Convention. Manncraft, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- TWUA Convention. Electing the Slate, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Merger Committee, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Merger. Salaries, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Merger. Agreement and Plan, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Merger. Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Merger Convention. Agenda, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Merger Convention. Committees, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Merger Convention. Decorations, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Merger Convention. Delegates, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Merger Convention. Dramatization. Owen Tapper, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Merger Convention. Entertainment, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Merger Convention. Exhibits, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Merger Convention. Hargrove, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Merger Convention. Marvin Himmel, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Merger Convention. Hotel Arrangements, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Merger Convention. Hotel Confirmation, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Merger Convention. Memorial, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Merger Convention. Rules for Elections and Voting on Merger, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Merger Convention. Simultaneous Translation, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Merger Convention. Staff Letters and Assignments, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Merger Convention. Staff Meeting, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Merger Convention. TWUA-ACWA Joint Meeting, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Merger Convention. To Do Folder. Pre-Convention, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Merger Convention. Bruce Raynor, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Merger Convention. Usher Management, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Merger Convention. Visual Aid Electronics. Bill Whalen, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. September 25, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. September 26, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Convention Transcript. Afternoon Session. September 26, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. September 27, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Convention Transcript. Afternoon Session. September 27, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. September 28, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Convention Transcript. Afternoon Session. September 28, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. September 29, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. June 3, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. June 4, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Convention Transcript. Morning Session. June 5, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Convention Committees and Sergeants-At-Arms, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Proposed Amendments to Constitution, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Proposed Resolutions, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Proposed Resolutions, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Copy 2
- Convention Unity, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  June 11-15, 1984
- Convention Transcript. June 11, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Unedited
- Convention Transcript. June 11, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Convention Transcript. June 11, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Copy 3
- Convention Transcript. June 12, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Convention Transcript. June 12, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Convention Transcript. June 12, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Convention Transcript. June 13, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Convention Transcript. June 13, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Convention Transcript. June 13, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Convention Transcript. June 14, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Convention Transcript. June 14, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Convention Transcript. June 14, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Convention Transcript. June 15, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Convention Transcript. June 15, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Convention Transcript. June 15, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Proposed Amendments to Constitution, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Proposed Resolutions, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Convention Committees and Sergeants-At-Arms, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Convention Unity, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  June 15-19, 1987
- Burt Beck. A Commitment to Progress, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Convention. Handouts, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Convention. Credentials, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Convention Transcript. Fisrt Session. June 15, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Convention Transcript. First Session. June 15, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Unedited. Copy 2
- Convention Transcript. Second Session. June 16, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Convention Transcript. Second Session. June 16, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Convention Transcript. Third Session. June 16, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Convention Transcript. Third Session. June 16, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Convention Transcript. Fourth Session. June 17, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Convention Transcript. Fourth Session. June 17, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Convention Transcript. Fifth Session. June 18, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Convention Transcript. Fifth Session. June 18, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Convention Transcript. Sixth Session. June 18, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Convention Transcript. Sixth Session. June 18, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Convention Transcript. Seventh Session. June 19, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Convention Transcript. Seventh Session. June 19, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Index File of Convention Committee Members, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  See also Box 1, Folder 19